Guide to the Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Eugène Jolas - Writings, 1879-1971; Series II; 6.75; (16 boxes)
  - BOOKS OF POEMS
    - Reporters
      - Section T - News from Germany (Box 16, Folder 306)
        - Reports of Angels
          - "We were in a glitzermood..." "In the heteroclite night..." "For we are the new men..." "LONDON NEWS-SHEET (1590)..." "Nous étions fatigués..."
          - "I wandered amid..." "We watched the artillery battle..." "The bells of Lyra ring..." "We think of the war..." "barbares nous inventons des mots..."
          - "We watched the artillery battle..." "Pulitzer we said oh giant..." "Oh wanderer through the western..." "Spring gleamed..." "Ok are you ready..."
          - "That fetching girl undid herself..." "Oh deep symbol of time we stood..." "The lobster shift creaks through..." "What was that..." oh magical..." "Here's London here's London..."
          - "We meditated Charlemagne's..." "And Lumor said man has grown..." "I said what are these sounds..." "The German words were decayed..." "A broken piano moaned down..." "Nous serons les hommes..."
      - Section Z - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 16, Folder 309)
        "The grey ships were lying..."
        "I remembered the titatic city..."
        "Our words were striated..."
        "I listened to the old man..."
        "Glory to you/Seekers of the Holy..."
        "In the year 2000 we shall live..."
    - Reporters (French)
      - Section A (Box 16, Folder 310)
        "Prologue..."
        "L'ombre de la maison..."
        "L'homme chelien était harcelé..."
        "On mourait d'exile/Dans la nuit..."
        "Voici les gens brisés..."
        "Je cheminais seul dans la petite..."
        "Les astéroides hérissés..."
        "Les feuilles rouanes tombaient..."
        "La vieille blessure..."
        "Le psaumier des blessures..."
        "Nous nous hations sous la pluie..."
        "On martelait dans le sousol..."
        "Ce n'était plus l'âge d'or
        "Mon rêve vecut de l'an mil..."
        "L'exode vers l'ouest s'arrete..."
        "Les visages etaient en transit..."
        "La misere était dans..."
        "Je vois la ville-frontiere..."
        "Les prisonniers crépitaient..."
        "Le faubourg regardait..."
        "La saison baroque se mourait..."
        "Le crépuscule luisait..."
        "Et Brusquement le soleil parla..."
        "J'ai dit tu ne m'attends plus..."
        "Le vent chantait une litanie..."
        "J'ai medité l'Europe..."
        "La tourmente était..."
        "Une hallucination nous entrainait..."
        "L'orage de lignite s'annonca..."
        "Nous écoutions les cris..."
        "La frontière attendait..."
        "Les années printanieres..."
        "Le film des révoltes..."
        "La grammaire est lacérée..."
        "Baal..."
        "Les ombres se faufilent..."
      - Section B (Box 16, Folder 311)
        "Dans la rue des taudis les mots..."
        "Mes mots etaient a cheval..."
        "Les mots de la mère..."
        "Les mots de mon pere revenaient..."
        "Mes mots étaient striés de sang..."
        "Les mots des contes magiques..."
        "Des voiles de fumee le long..."
        "Je me souviens de la ville..."
      - Section C (Box 16, Folder 312)
        "Mes mots amérigraient..."
        "Je vois colmar indechiffrable
        "Je me rappelle, la nuit..."
        "La ville alsatienne soupirait..."
      - Section D
        "La frontière s'ouvrait..."
        "Les lépreux rencontraient..."
        "Nous etions debout dans le halo..."
        "Ou est était souffle..."
        "Toute la grammaire..."
        "J'ai dit Je te salue..."
        "Les dialogues fumaient..."
        "Un grand espoir s'endormait..."
        "Une misere envahit les yeux..."
      - Section E (Box 16, Folder 313)
        "Je me rappelle le Rhin martyre..."
        "J'ai dit: Tous les mots du foyer..."
        "L'été de flammes se chamaillait..."
        "Je vois les jeunes rêveurs..."
        "La vie pneumatique."
        "Nous éveillions le souvenir..."
        "J'etais devant la plaine du Rhin..."
        "Je regardai la liturgie..."
        "La ville bâtie très haut..."
        "J'ai dit a mon camarade..."
        "Les mots s'enfuyaient..."
        "Nous sentions les images..."
        "Le paysage prolétarien..."
        "Des mots-machine houlaient..."
        "Ici le post WYOP..."
        "Maintenant tous les chemins..."
        "Etalé dans la vallee..."
        "Et je me rappelais les mots..."
        "Et je marchais dans mon Amerique..."
        "Donde estan las estrellas..."
        "Il reve la nouvelle langue..."
      - Section F (Box 16, Folder 314)
        Reporters
        "Le tumulte des téléscripteurs..."
        "We come from many lands we speak..."
        "We were the men who brought..."
        "Les années printanières..."
        "Les sagaroses se risettent..."
      - Section G
        "Nous avons ronaqué les lullas..."
        "L'angoisse de la vie frissonnait..."
        "Les mots-drames flambent."
        "Les meraballes flinten..."
        "Nebulasol luit..."
        "Nous sommes dans un souvenir..."
    - Selected Poems
      - Master List, 1920-1940 (Box 17, Folder 315)
      - Farandole, 1934 (Box 17, Folder 316)
      - Manticana
        Passage of the demi-urge
        Flight to the number
        De statu animae
        Decomposition of grunewald
        The hermes season
      - Verbirrupta of the third eye
        Exit of the bell
        Triangle
        Experience of the hour
      - Anamyth Arrival of x Mexico Wrinkled History Open world Alamasatl
      - Note for Master Eckhardt Strophades Silvalogue
      - Neologos
        1. Rodeur
        2. Dusk
        3. Gulf
        4. Story
      - Timeling Cosmogrammes
      - Conspiracy in light Incantation Hunger Choral, 1927
      - Hymn, 1928
      - Psalm, 1931
      - Vineyard in Sun Mater Dolorosa Guatemala Mountain Words
      - To the Tremendum Australia Arra Glitz and Glast Cosmogrammes
      - Decision The Battlefield Nomads The romantic Arcadia
      - Resouvenir At Watch, 1936
      - Minne, 1933
      - Heartling Prayer on the Titantower, 1936
      - Equivocables of the Mountainmen
      - Timeling Chellesiad Wildworld Glintstroll Choirprair
      - Demon ringsings mysticana flor in/ Catacombtumult of Lighthour Sion Anthologie Blasée Dernière édition
      - Voyage Sentimental Confiteor The Vision The Drill Field Dawn
      - Portrait of the Exile Manhattan Unrest The Wedding Decomposition Requiem for My Youth
      - Psalm Migration Elegy
      - Almanach for Quetzolcoatl All Things are Mine Pilgrimage Pastorale (Box 17, Folder 317)
      - Cinema Poems
        Cinéma du Verbe
        Manhattan Films
        Cinema Songs
      - Atlantic Vision Ink Lament Advice to Myself To a Lost Friend
      - Interlude Songs During a Tempest Ashaverus, 1912-13
      - Amerika Sehnsucht nach dem Western
      - Skyscraper Nocturne Der Kerker Autumn Voyage Ecstatic Chant Nachtlied
      - Faula and Flona In the Street Jungle The Apocalyptic Hour, 1936
      - Hymn for the Others Vagabond
      - Die Landung The Numinous Hunger Note to Another Civilization Paradox Before Press Time
      - Frank Nolan, Private Detective Song of Deliverance Wolkenkratzer-Gedicht Notschrei Abendhyme (Box 17, Folder 318)
      - Meditation The Call The Job-Hunter West Street Pastel Intuitions
      - V The Scribblers Ete Messin Hunger Prayer Before Christ of Grunewald
      - The Grey Days Danse des Morts Panic in a City Illusion of Light Offering of Jazz
      - Description of Snow The Question The Visionary Moselle The Prisoner
      - The Fever The Dreamer On a Sky-Scraper Nocturne on a New York Sky-Scraper Love-Song in Winter
      - Going down the Bay Metamorphosis The Rebels Political Convention In a Train
      - The Fetish The Dreamer The Manichean Confessing Futility Revolt against Dogma
      - Challenge of the Age Doubt-Faith-Doubt For Those who are Weary of Big Cities The Voyage Antigone
      - Berlin Snapshot Mood Chant for an Illusion in a taxi
      - Mummers The Hudson Heimweh Hunger New England Night
      - Stanzas of Love Renaissance Linotype Words about Cities Nocturne
      - Dialogue Jack Brown of North Carolina Another Negro The Bat The Idiot
      - Words in a Police Station Jazzband On an Old Newspaper Found in the Streets The Strikers Alien Portrait
      - Protest Caprice Desert Cry Darkness Broods The Town Library
      - Lines for a Vagabond Poet Who is Anchored in a\ Gray City Movie Metempsychosis Nocturne in a Factory Town Strike Night-Metamorphosis Hunger Factory Girls Psychopathic Personality (Emotional Instability)
      - D.T. Psychastenia The Nurse Bockstanz Noon
      - Strasbourg Conspiracy of Light Arrival of the Whimsies Promenade Thunderbloom
      - Possession Stanzas of Youth Evocation for Jacques Abend am Meer, 1912
      - Le Possédé
      - The Peasant Prière Les tortures Poste de police Portrait d'un reporter
      - Le Spectre Panorama Coda Minuit Nostalgia Salle de Rédaction
      - Rhythmes d'Automne The Exiles
      - V American Hymn Metamorphose de la Sainte, 1933
      - By Radio to God (Box 17, Folder 319)
        Wireless of my heart
      - By Radio to God
        La Négation
        Rhythmes Angoisses
        Illusion
        Symbole
      - Transcendental Vaudeville
        The Ballet
        Song and Dance Men
        The Mississippi Boat
        The Gospel Train
        Feature Film
        Acrobats
        Prayer of Steel
        Jazz Orchestra with Psalms
        Strike Episode
        Little Italy
        The God Seeker
      - Reporters Les reporters
      - The Book of Fools
        - The House of Fools Lines about a Bathtub, 1917-18
        - Entrelacs The Moran D.P. (Paranoiac) Dementia Praecox
      - Letter to a friend in prison Document
      - Three Cities
        Paris
        While the cities dance
      - Planets and Angels (Mount Vernon, Iowa) (Box 17, Folder 320)
        "Planets and Angels..."
        "Vertical 2-This is a landscape..."
        "A swarm of seraphim flutters..."
        "Titanic armies of cherubim pass..."
        "What is this faroff you..."
        "The angel Lumor walks with us..."
        "Lumor came to us/When our hearts..."
        "Lumor came in the deep-sleep..."
        "And everything here grows into U..."
        "Angry is the angel Lumor..."
        "The children cried..."
        "There was an old tree..."
        "La jeune fille française..."
        "La grammaire était lacerée..."
        "We came from many lands..."
        "We gave the news of the war..."
        "Le reporter tapait sur la machine..."
        "I stood before my father's grave..."
        "We slowly ascended the tower under the grey
        "skies..."
        "We were fatigued in the grey lobstershift..."
        "They remembered in the incendiary psamls..."
        "La grande migration is not yet over in our time..."
        "We were reporters in the huge cosmopolis..."
        "The dusk of the occident is full of dust..."
        - "Here are some of the sketches I wrote..." "One night we heard the crashgrunt..." "La titanecaisse nuitroule des mastragrettes..." "toute la nuit un mot..." "Une voix tocsine le feufou de la foret, 1933..."
        - "Un succube sangsuce..."
        - "Noon was bruised..." "Tears...", 1935
        - "nima oortin frol anatinka, 1934
        - "Lustrala gloseelee..."
        - Title sheets (Box 17, Folder 321)
    - Vertical
      - Printed text, 1938 (Box 17, Folder 322)
    - Wanderpoem
      - Titled Fragments
        - Pittsburgh (Box 17, Folder 323)
          Milltown
          "The three rivers are mistenshrouded..."
          Sunday-Evening in the Hill District
          Main Street -- 11 p.m.
          Ennui
          "The masses flee the acrid bombloads..."
          "We quit Europe in a troubleboat..."
        - The South
          Euramerican Chant
        - Panamerican Journey
          Hymns of Ascent
        - Midwest Poems
          "We were wanderers..."
          The Bible-Romance
        - "In Metz I looked again..." "June flimmers over..." Apocalypse Prologue to Emmigrants Montreal Mississippi
        - Rhenus Holy Week 1946 Epilogue Dead Cities War
        - June 1945 Migration in Multilingual America Immigrants
        - The Immigrants Migration Immigrants
      - Untitled Fragments, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 324)
      - Notes, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 325)
      - Clippings, 1945, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 326)
    - Words From the Deluge
      - Advertisement, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 327)
      - Printed Text, 1941
  - POEMS AS ORGANIZED BY MARIA JOLAS
    - English
      - Master List (Box 18, Folder 328)
      - Nostalgia for Liturgy Alone From: Landscapes Wireless Words from America (Box 18, Folder 329)
      - Rhythms for Sanity - (Proofs)
        Note to Another Civilization
      - My Radio to God
        Wireless of my Heart
        Panic in a City
        Illusion of Light
        Confessing Futility
        Offering of Jazz
        Intuitions
        Words in a Police Station
        Revolt Against Dogma
        Challenge of the Age
        Doubt-Faith-Doubt
        Danse des Morts
        The Rebels
        Political Convention
        In a Train "Frankfort-Berlin"
        Words about Cities
        Jazzband
        The Fetish
      - Babel 1939 (with unidentified holograph notes)
      - Verbirrupta of the Third Eye
        Exit of the Bell
        Experience of the Hour
        Note for Master Eckehart
        Decomposition of Grunewald
        The Hermes Season
        Wildworld
        Glintstroll
        Choirprair
        Equivocables of the Mountainmen
        Timeling
        Chellesiad
        Anamyth
        Arrival of X
        Wrinkled History
        Open World
        Conspiracy in Light
        Verbirrupta of the Mountainmen
        Alamasatl
        Migration Elegy
      - Manticana
        Passage of the Demi-Urge
        Flight to the Number
        De Statu Animae
      - At Watch, 1936
      - Lament Decision Ink Paradox
      - Before Press-Time Western Exhoration Armageddon Chant of the Word-men
      - Prayers in Time of Anguish Ode to the Frontiermen News From a Brother in 1941 Westering Epic (Box 18, Folder 330)
      - Nostalgia for the Fourth Dimension
        Third Eye
        Ode to the Cosmos
      - Sidereals
      - Sidereals
        The Sidereal Pilgrims
      - Sidereal Ascent Immigrant's Return Hymn to Uninations Amerikafahrer Poem News Sheet Poem
      - Holderlin (p. 2 & 3) New York Tabloid Words Exorcisms Angelic Perspectives
      - Night in Alsace After a Columbiad "The canticle of the moon..." "I have met you on the three nation border..." "The big sky jeep came flying..." (Box 18, Folder 331)
      - "consolation in firerain..." "Umbruch say the Germans..." Voluptas XVI "October night swales..." "cliffcrystalhouses..."
      - "We remember the gravity..." "With the hammer-verbs..." "The ghost of a dreamer..." The Numinous Hour (printed page) "the wounded machine lingered..."
      - "We came from Europe's malady..." "the ghost of a dreamer..." Preface Crucible The Crucible City Requiem for a Lorraine Town
      - The Lorraine town of my childhood weeps "I had the Germans..." "In this French canteen..." "unhappy troglodites..." "I dreamed of her last night..."
      - "We were in many printing plants..." Strasbourg Epilogue "We came to the newspaper plant..." "walking through the anonymous streets..."
      - "we were in the city rooms..." "almageste of chaos..." "stormtime and the ooze..." "I heard the planes..." "that night when we heard..."
      - "midnight thunders darkly..." "I mused in this old land..." "We heard the words of the FFI..."
      - Lorraine Requiem: 1945 Frankfurt Saga Voyages Sans Fin Myth of Migrations in My Creative Poetry Skyscrapers
      - Notes and Fragments (Box 18, Folder 332)
    - French
      - Master List, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 333)
      - La Nuit Verticale Ascension au Tremendum Cinema du Verbe Poeme Eschatologique Chant Funebre pour Jean Arthus (Box 18, Folder 334)
      - Le Merveilleux d'Outre-Ciel, 1937
      - Les Mots pleuvaient doucement Pentecôte dans la Vie Ruinée Ressouvenir Ete Messin
      - Lorraine Youth Priere sur le Mont Ste. Odile Ode a Manhattan Monologue La Légion
      - Air - Lily Marlene La Complainte du Partisan
      - Montreal/Mississippi/Nouvelle Orleans
        Montreal ou les voyageurs
        Atlantic Chants
        Le Mississippi
      - Retour a la Frontiere Retour au Rhin Gratteciels Voyage vers le Soleil (Box 18, Folder 335)
      - Sidereal (Poèmes) (Box 18, Folder 336)
        Langage de la Voie Lactée
        Voyage à la planète Luminella
        Lumenella
        "Nous autres reporters..."
        "Hiver sans merci..."
        "Nous quittions les plages..."
        "Le jour fauve..."
        "Dans l'heure sans etoiles..."
        "Les bateaux en rade..."
        "L'idiome se lassait..."
        "Elle etait toujours la..."
        "Apres le long voyage..."
        "Cette lettre d'outre-mer..."
        "Les bourgeois tuaient..."
        "La machine etait une obsession..."
        "Mes mots étainet battailleurs..."
        "The miraculous machine..."
        "Je voyais la ville noire..."
        "Nous etions invites a une fete..."
        "Les mots du reporter..."
        "Le joug de la journee..."
        "Douleur de l'universe..."
        "Camarades dis-je Babylon..."
        "La sierene d'en face..."
        "Arret dans la village..."
        "Le peuple trainait..."
        "Angoisse de New York..."
        "Quelle etait cette angoisse..."
        "Nous etions des etrangers..."
        "J'avais voyagé en jeep à travers..."
        "lestribus accroupies devant..."
        "Camarades babylon..."
        "Je me rappelle France..."
        "Je pensais a tous les fleuves..."
        "Nous etions couverts...."
        "rivieres du monde..."
        "j'attendait a toison d'or..."
        "Une eclogue stellaire..."
        "la flore et faune..."
        "complaintes de l'amour..."
        "vertiges du press..."
        "les moulagoues..."
        "nous revions toujours..."
        "nous battons contre les portes..."
        "je trainais dans les villes..."
        "C'etait dans la guerre..."
        "Nous quittions les plages Greles..."
        "Le soir d'ete etait..."
        "L'angoisse de la vie..."
        "La peur était toujours avec moi..."
        "La grammaire était lacérée..."
        "Dans cette heure de peche..."
        "La rivière coule à travers..."
        "Nous avons ronaqué les lulas..."
        "La machinelle nous balbatisse..."
        "Les vetements des metaphores..."
        "Nous appareillons toujours..."
        "Je suis de nouveau..."
        "Voici l'angoisse de l'homme..."
        "la vie hermaphrodite attend..."
        "Nous étions ensemble dans..."
        "La belle colette avait des..."
        "Merveilleuse était la vente..."
        "Les gars du maquis travaillaient..."
        "nuit sans merci nuit lepreuse..."
        "Je me rappelle une femme entre..."
        "Je quitte le building..."
        "Et la Seine coule vers..."
    - Migrations - Table of contents and title pages
    - French with English translations
      typescript and holograph, corrected
      - "femme s'habillant dans une chambre d'hotel...", n.d. (Box 18, Folder 337)
      - "woman dressing in a hotel-room..."
    - German
      typescript, typescript carbon and holograph,
      corrected
      - Master list (Box 18, Folder 338)
      - Erdleben, 1947
      - Cosmogrammes Sidereals Mit Zagen Lippen Choreographie des Sommers
      - Andenken Balance Herbstwind Tischgesellschaft Die Metamorphose
      - Crucible Poem 1941 Berthold Viertel-Die Deutsche Sprache Dad-Ode
      - Ode an die Reporter
      - "Am Festtag arbeiten wir..." "Die apokalyptischen Reiter..." "Eure Worte sind mit Blut..." "Der Kantilenen der Liebe..." "Wessen Schuld schreib ich?"
      - "Immer leuchtete..." "Dunkle Wolken jagen..." "Lange tieftraumschliefen wir..." "Ich hoere dich noch..." "Die Moewen kreischen..."
      - "Draussen seien der Mond..." "Immer noch hoer ich..." Der Schiffer im Kahne [and others] (Printed text) "Der Polizeireporter..." "Ich komme aus Amerika..."
      - Der himmel, 1911
      - Für Maria Grenze
    - Multilingual
      - Master List, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 339)
      - Incantations (Box 18, Folder 340)
        - Choral, 1927
        - Hymn, 1928
        - Psalm, 1931
      - Vineyard in Sun
      - Incantation Alchemical Chant Heartling Prayer on the Titantower, 1936
      - Minne, 1933
      - Mater Dolorosa, 1934
      - Astralia Arra Mountain words Guatemala Glitz and Glast
      - Farandole, 1934
      - Hymn to Supramerica
      - Neologos
        Rodeur
        Dusk
        Gulf
        Story
      - Faula and Flona Silvalogue Strophades Atomica, 1950
      - Weltangst
      - America Romantica Ete Messin Colmar Rhine-Town Matthias Grunewald
      - Dream of Portoricunla Logocinema of the Frontiermen Chochula Cantate de l'Uno
      - Atlantica Montreal Poem - Eloge a la Valle The Frontier Poem for the U.S. Army Strasbourg et la Vie sans frontières (Box 19, Folder 341)
      - immer leuchtete das woerterbuch..." "The demented cried..." Tears, 1935
      - Wiedersehen avec Manhattan "The taal de l'amour was a blick..." "The city was asleep and we were..."
      - "With a colossal cycle..." (fragment) "La titanecaisse nuitroule..." "We were immersed in the thundersurf..." "Here are some of the sketches..." "I recalled "Frontier Poem"..."
      - "le mythe continue comme un voyage..." "Summernight falls on the city..." "tous les etres migrateurs sont..."
      - Manhattan Poem (Fragments) Manhattan Migration Unbabel "You walk with me again..." "in the thickening dusk of paris..."
      - "silence dans la grande ville..." "in the blackout the voices whisper..." "on third avenue the bars..." "Nightern clung to summer..." "in the elevated train..."
      - "il n'y a qu'une seule ville..." "the GI talks to the young girl..." Metamorphosis Series
      - "but alaglast i mona een..." "leschamps elysees..." "Far-aching we remembered..." Exorcist Interludes (Fragments)
  - OTHER POEMS
    See also: Series XII - Transition General
    - Office Files - Contributions, Box 59 folder 1372
    - Ahnungen, printed version Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1932 Jul
      See: Oversize, Box 67, folder 1580
    - Appel orphique, printed version Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1932 Apr
    - Auf eine Zeiting in der Gosse, printed version Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1932 Dec
    - Aus dem "Amerikafahrer," printed version Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1931 Dec
    - Aus dem "Amerikafahrer," printed version Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1932 Feb
    - Berglied fur Betsy und Tina, printed version Revue du Rhin, 1938 Aug (Box 19, Folder 342)
    - Berglied fur Betsy und Tina, 1938 Aug (Box 19, Folder 343)
    - Requiem für Quetzalcoatl (Für Stuart Gilbert), 1932
    - Lorraine Summer (For Mother and Father), 1932
    - Fragment aus Einem Leben (Für Henri Solveen), 1932
    - Metamorphose, 1926
    - Alte lothringische Stadt, 1926
    - Arkadien, 1926
    - Ecstatic Chant, 1924
    - Hymn for America's Youth, 1924
    - Resouvenir, 1924
    - Rhythmen des Trotzes, 1923
    - List of titles, n.d.
    - (all typescript)
    - Euramerican Chant, printed version Fantasy, 1940 (Box 19, Folder 344)
    - Die Geier Stimmen aus Lothringen, 1932 Mar (Box 19, Folder 345)
    - Glitz and Glast Cosmogrammes, 1933 (Box 19, Folder 346)
    - Minne, 1933
    - Farandole, 1934
    - Arra, 1935
    - At Watch, 1936
    - Heartling Prayer on the Titantower, 1936
    - Mater Dolorosa Guatemala Mountain Words
    - To the Tremendum Astralia pages from I Have Seen Monsters and Angels, 1938